So in the last video we discovered how you can use the game Tennis
在上一期视频中 我们介绍了如何使用游戏《网球》
to get to glitched levels in Super Mario Bros.
来触发《超级马里奥兄弟》的“水下256关”
If you haven't seen that video yet, I highly suggest watching that video first.
如果还没有看过 墙裂建议先去看看
注：自译熟肉BV1Be411E7xZ，在阿婆的空间可以找到
In this video we'll see why the glitch levels we see
在本期视频中将会分析为什么触发的异常关卡
can be weird versions of levels that are normally found in the game.
有可能是游戏里正常关卡的诡异变种
Just like level 9-1 here being level 6-2 but underwater!
比如说这里的关卡9-1就是关卡6-2的水下版本
There are 34 unique 'levels' in Super Mario Bros.
《超级玛丽奥兄弟》中有34个不同的所谓“关卡”
注：这里所述的“关卡”是广义表述，倒不如说是“场景”更为合适
Well, there are 32 levels,
游戏本身有32关
but a lot of them are duplicates.
但很多关卡是重复的
Like for example, level 5-3 is just level 1-3
比如说关卡5-3和关卡1-3实际上是相同的
but there's Bullet Bills flying around and the platforms are shorter.
只是关卡5-3中有子弹头飞来飞去 并且浮动平台要更短些
注："Bullet Bills"即所谓“比尔子弹”，设定是反派:鲍瑟·库帕（Bowser Koopa）控制下的“比尔玩具枪”发射出的黑色子弹
There's a flag in the game that can convert a level into a harder version of itself,
游戏中有一个将某个关卡转换为困难版的标志
so for our purposes here, these are considered the same level.
所以在分析中 我们将这些关卡视为同一个
This leaves us with 27 unique levels.
如此 就只剩下27个不同的关卡了
Then you have the 2 cloud bonus rooms,
此外 还应该算上2个位于云彩上方可以吃硬币的空间
注：关卡2-1和5-2的藤曼爬上去到达白天版本的加分空间， 而关卡3-1和6-2的藤曼爬上去到达黑夜版本的加分空间
the warp zone in 4-2,
注："Warp Zone"，直译为“扭曲地带”，通向其它世界的黑洞；关卡4-2中从藤曼机关爬上去到达跳关区，可以选择进入第6/7/8个世界
关卡1-2借助上升平台跳上屋顶，也有个跳关区，通往世界2/3/4，但它是关卡1-2的一部分，而4-2的跳关区是独立场景（载入时屏幕黑一下）
和关卡4-2中允许跳关的区域
the water room in 8-4,
还有关卡8-4中出现的水下空间
注：在关卡8-4，从地图一半左右位置的一根管子钻下去，进入这片水下空间
and the water room used in both 5-2 and 6-2.
以及另一个在关卡5-2和6-2中共用的水下空间
And then finally the cutscene room that plays before underground and water levels,
再算上这个在地下和水下关卡之前播放的过场区域
as well as the underground bonus rooms
最后还有这片位于地下的加分空间
which are actually all located in the same level.
所有地下的加分空间实际上位于同一个场景中
Each of the 34 levels is assigned a unique ID of sorts.
这34个关卡（场景） 的每一个都被分配了独一无二的标识码（ID）
But if you think the ID numbers are simply just 0 through 33, you are sorely mistaken.
但如果你认为ID只是简单地从0编号到33 那就大错特错了
See, the ID for each level also encodes what kind of level it is.
每一关的ID还编码有关卡类型
There are four types of levels: overworld, underground, castle, and water.
关卡的类型有四种 分别为主世界 地下 城堡和水下
Each of the levels is organized into these four groups,
每个关卡都被归入这四组之一
and then numbers are assigned within each group.
再对每组内的关卡分别进行编号
Water levels have numbers 0-2,
水下关卡被编号为0到2
overworld levels have numbers 0-21,
主世界关卡的编号是0到21
underground levels have numbers 0-2,
地下关卡的编号是0到2
and castle levels have numbers 0-5.
城堡关卡的编号是0到5
The overall ID of a level is made up of 7 bits.
完整的关卡ID一共有7位
The lower 5 bits are the level number within the sublist.
低5位是关卡在组内的编号
And the next 2 bits are the level type,
而更高的2位表示关卡类型
注：也就是说，关卡ID是位图（Bitmap）表示，将位分组，每组都是可解释的
这里“标识码”或"ID"的表述和第一集中“世界编号”相区分，后者是游戏中世界自然地按序编号，而非位图
where water is 00, overworld is 01, underground is 10, and castle is 11.
0b00表示水下 0b01表示主世界 0b10表示地下 0b11表示城堡
注：和C语言一样，字幕使用"0x"前缀表示十六进制，使用"0b"表示二进制
This means that the ID of a level can range anywhere from 0 to $7F,
这意味着关卡ID的范围是从0到0x7F
注：即一个字节的8位中只有7位有效，最高位始终为0
although most IDs aren't used.
即使其中有很多并没有被游戏使用
We can organize them in a nice table like this.
据此 我们将关卡重新组织成这样一张美观的表格
For water levels, the type bits are 00, so the overal IDs are $00 through $02.
对于水下关卡 表示类型的位是0b00 因而ID的范围是0x00到0x02
For overworld levels, the type bits are 01, so the IDs go from $20 to $35.
对于主世界关卡 类型位是0b01 ID从0x20取到0x35
For underground levels, the bits are 10, and the IDs go from $40 to $42.
水下关卡的类型位是0b10 ID从0x40取到0x42
And for castle levels, the bits are 11, so the IDs go from $60 to $65.
最后 城堡关卡的类型是0b11 ID从0x60取到0x65
So an interesting question would be:
这引出了一个有趣的问题
What about all these other IDs that aren't assigned to levels; what do they do?
那些没有被分配到关卡的ID又怎么样呢？它们会有用吗？
To answer this we have to look at how the level pointers are stored in the game's ROM.
为了回答 先来了解关卡指针是怎样存储在游戏ROM里的
There are actually four separate pointer lists,
事实上 存在四个指针数组
two for all the level's tile data,
两个用于所有关卡的图块数据
and two for all the level's enemy and sprite data.
而另外两个用于所有关卡的敌人和精灵数据
注：“图块”和“精灵”是早期2D游戏图像绘制中的概念，红白机PPU的设计中有直接对应
“图块”一般指可重复利用的位图图元，“精灵”是游戏里的可动区域（一般是游戏中的角色或其它需要检查碰撞的元素）
这里借用了以上的高级语义，指针指向的内容是游戏编程中的结构，并不一定直接指向PPU绘制绑定的相关内存区域，具体请看下集
The level pointers are 16-bit values,
每个关卡指针都是16位的数据
注：16位地址可以覆盖6502 CPU的整个内存地址空间
and to simplify the code needed to read data from these tables,
为了使从这些数组中读取数据的代码变得简单
the upper 8 bits are stored in one list, while the lower 8 bits are stored in another list.
指针的高8位被存入一个数组 而低8位被存入另一个数组
This way if you want, say, the 13th pointer in the list,
在这样的设计下 如果需要从数组中读取第13个指针
you take the 13th byte in each list and concatenate them together to get a 16-bit pointer.
就需要从每个半指针数组中分别取出第13个字节 再将它们拼接成一个16位的指针
In the table of IDs we made, there are gaps inbetween the different types of levels.
在之前的ID表格中 不同类型的关卡之间 ID并不连续
However, the pointers to the level data are stored in one contiguous chunk.
但指向关卡数据的指针被存放在一个连续的块中
For the sprite data, all of the castle levels come first and have indices 0 to 5,
在精灵数据的指针数组中 城堡关卡在最前面 数组索引是0到5
then the overworld levels in order 6 to 27,
紧接着是索引为6到27的主世界关卡
then the underground levels 28 to 30, and finally the water levels 31 to 33.
然后是地下关卡 索引为28到30 最后是水下关卡 索引为31到33
For the tile data though, all of the water levels come first with indices 0 to 2,
图块数据的指针数组顺序有所不同 所有水下关卡排在最前面（索引为0到2）
then the overworld levels 3 to 24,
此后索引3到24是主世界关卡
then the underground levels 25 to 27,
索引25到27是地下关卡
followed by the castle levels 28 to 33.
索引28到33是城堡关卡
Who knows why they are stored in a different order,
不清楚开发者为什么要按照不同的顺序存储这些数据
because it just make things more complicated and nuanced!
这样只是使得情况变得更加复杂和微妙
In order to easily access each of the different types of levels,
为了便于访问到不同类型的关卡
there are also two smaller tables that indicate the offsets at which each of the different types start in this list,
另有两个用于指示不同类型关卡在大数组中开始位置（偏移量）的小数组
in the order of water, overworld, underground, and castle.
小数组的组织顺序是：水下-主世界-地下-城堡
注：这个顺序和关卡ID位图最高两位表示关卡类型的设计相统一，可以位操作分离出ID所有7位的高两位，直接索引小数组
Think of this as a sort of table of contents
可以把小数组当作某种意义上的“目录”
It's just like page at the start of a book that tells you where each chapter starts.
和书本最前面几页会告诉你每一章从哪里开始是一个道理
So for the sprite data, this table is just $1F, $06, $1C, $00.
因此 对于精灵数据 小数组中的四个元素分别为0x1F 0x06 0x1C和0x00
Remember all the indices mentioned in this video are zero-based,
不要忘记 视频中提到的所有索引都是从0开始的
so water levels start at index 31 ($1F),
所以水下关卡从索引31或0x1F开始
overworld levels at index 6,
主世界关卡从索引6开始
underground levels at index 28 ($1C),
地下关卡从索引28或0x1C开始
and castle levels at index 0.
而城堡关卡从索引0开始
And the table for the tile data is just $00, $03, $19, $1C.
同理 图块数据的小数组中四个元素是0x00 0x03 0x19和0x1C
In order to find a certain level in this list,
为了得到大数组中指向某个关卡的指针
we take its level number and add it to the index that corresponds to the level's type.
我们需要取得关卡在组内的编号 把它和对应关卡类型的索引相加（再去索引大数组）
For example, level 6-2 has ID $23, which corresponds to overworld level number 3.
比如说 关卡6-2的ID是0x23 对应主世界组中的3号关卡
For the tile data, overworld levels start at index 3, so we add that to 3 to get 6,
对于图块数据指针而言 主世界关卡从索引3开始 计算3加3得到6
so the tile data is the 7th entry in this list.
因此这一关的图块数据指针对应图块指针数组中的第7个元素
And for the sprite data, overworld levels start at index 6,
对于精灵数据指针 主世界关卡从索引6开始
so we add that to 3 to get 9, and the sprite data is the 10th entry in this list.
我们将6加上3得到9 所以精灵数据指针是对应大数组中的第10个元素
So now we can see what would happen if we were to try to load, say, the level with ID $43.
接下来我们尝试加载ID为0x43的关卡 看看会发生什么
This corresponds to underground level number 3,
它对应编号为3的地下关卡
and of course, there is no underground level number 3.
然而 地下关卡中并没有编号为3的关卡
But the calculation is still performed.
但上述计算照做不误
For tile data, underground levels start at index 25, so we add 3 to that to get 28,
地下关卡的图块数据指针从索引25开始 我们将关卡编号3加上去得到索引28
and we find the 29th entry in the list is the tile data for level 1-4.
我们在图块指针数组中找到第29个元素 它指向关卡1-4的图块数据
And for sprite data, underground levels start at index 28, so we add 3 to that to get 31,
地下关卡的精灵数据指针从索引28开始 给它加上3得到索引31
and we find the 32th entry in the list is the sprite data for water sublevel found in level 5-2.
我们找到精灵指针数组的第32个元素 它是指向水下关卡5-2的精灵数据的指针
This means, we will end up with a Frankenstein level that is level 1-4
这导致我们得到了一个怪异的关卡 它基于关卡1-4的地图
but with an underground theme with the Bloopers and platforms from that water sublevel all mixed together.
虽然拥有地下风格的主题 但也融合了指定水下关卡的章鱼怪（Bloopers）和移动平台
Which is exactly what we get when we force the game to load in the level with ID $43.
这就是强制游戏去加载ID为0x43的关卡导致的结果
注：综上所示，这种“混合关卡”的成因是未经检查的数组子区域越界访问
Since there are only 34 entries in these lists, if we ever end up with an index of 34 or higher,
由于每个指针数组都只有34个元素 如果使用大于等于34的索引去访问它
we start to read things that aren't pointers to level data.
就会读取到并不指向有效关卡数据的“野指针”
This is what causes glitch levels to appear, which we'll see happen in a bit.
这导致了异常关卡的产生 这种情况我们稍后再来讲解
But knowing all this, we can fill out the rest of the table we made
按照这个原则 我们来补齐表格中空缺的位置
to see what levels will get loaded for the level IDs that aren't assigned to anything.
继续研究在使用未分配的关卡ID时载入关卡的形态
Since the level data is stored in a different order for sprites versus tile data,
对于精灵数据和图块数据来说 关卡数据的存储顺序并不相同
levels with these unused IDs are either a mix of two different levels,
那些无用ID所对应的关卡 可能是两个不同的正常关卡的混合
a normal level layout with glitched sprites,
也可能是正常关卡布局和不正常精灵数据的组合
a glitched level layout with normal sprites, or both glitched tile data and sprite data.
又或者是异常的关卡布局搭配正常的精灵 也有可能图块和精灵数据都是异常的
But how does the game even try to load a glitched level ID in the first place?
但是 游戏最开始是怎样得到一个异常的关卡ID并尝试载入它的呢？
In order for the game to know what levels are in which worlds, and what order they go in,
为了得知每个世界有哪些关卡 以及这些关卡进入的顺序
there is a single table that holds the ID of each level in the order they are played.
游戏中有一个存储着全部关卡ID的数组 其中的关卡按游玩顺序存放
注：为了方便表达，下面称它为“关卡ID数组”
So for example, starting with world 1: level 1-1 is an overworld level so it has type bits 01.
举例来说 从1号世界开始 关卡1-1是一个主世界关卡 它的类型位是0b01
It has the level number of 5, so this is what its ID looks like, which is $25 in hexadecimal.
同时它的组内关卡编号是5 所以它的关卡ID是十六进制的0x25
This is the first byte in the table.
这就是关卡ID数组的第一个字节
Here is the rest of the table, which coresponds to each of the other levels.
这些是数组的其它元素 对应游戏的其它关卡的ID
If I split them up per world, you can see that some worlds actually have 5 levels.
如果将这个数组按世界划分 可以发现事实上某些世界有5个关卡
This is because the cutscene room that plays before the underground and water levels is actually considered its own level.
这是因为在进入地下或水下关卡前 过场区域被当作独立的关卡
Which was probably done so that if you die in one of these levels, you don't have to watch the cutscene again.
这样设计的原因可能是防止玩家在某一关失败以后 过场动画被重复播放
注：把过场动画制作在关卡头部，就会出现游戏失败后重复播放的情况
Since each world can have a different number of levels in it,
由于每个世界包含的关卡数量可能不一样
it would be nice to have some pointers into this table that tell where each of the worlds start.
一个好的设计是使用另一组数据指向这个数组中的位置 告知每个世界从哪里开始
Just like another table of contents like before with the level data pointers.
和之前关卡数据指针的“目录”类似 这也是一个“目录”
Here, there are 8 bytes in ROM directly before this table,
在ROM中关卡ID数组的前面 紧挨着存放有一个8字节的小数组
which are the indices of the first levels of each world.
里面正是每个世界第一关在关卡ID数组中的索引
So world 1 has index 0, world 2 has index 5, and so on.
1号世界的索引是0 而2号世界的索引是5 以此类推
So let's do a small example to try to get the pointers to the level data for the first level in world 3.
下面通过一个简单的示例 来说明如何取得3号世界的第一关的关卡数据指针
World 3 would correspond an index of 2 into this first table, or the 3rd entry, which is 10 ($0A).
3号世界对应头一个小数组的2号索引 即第三个元素 从中得到数据10或0x0A
So we use this index 10 to find the 11th entry into the level ID table,
使用10作为索引 找到关卡ID数组中第11个元素
which looks like it is $24.
这里是0x24
According to our big table,
依照我们先前整理的大表格
the level with ID $24 is level 3-1, but let's see how the level data pointers are created.
0x24这个关卡ID对应关卡3-1 先不管这个 来看看如何使用它构建出关卡数据指针
Expand that ID out into binary and we can see that this level uses 01 as its type,
我们将这个关卡ID展开为二进制 可以得到它的关卡类型是0b01
so it is an overworld level.And it's number 4.
这说明它是个主世界关卡 同时组内的关卡编号为4
First let's find the sprite data.
先来处理精灵数据指针
The 2 bits for the level type are actually used as the index into the smaller table we made for the level data type groups.
编码关卡类型的两个比特被用来索引小数组 我们拿它来找到对应关卡类型的一组关卡数据指针
Our bits are 01, so we use index 1, or the 2nd entry in this table, which is 6.
关卡类型是0b01 对应的索引是1 读出小数组的第二个元素 即6
Then we add that with the level number we got, so 6 plus 4 is 10.
我们把6和组内关卡编号4相加 得到10
So we use this index 10 to find the 11th entry in the level table,
再根据索引10 读取精灵数据指针数组的第11个元素
which is the address $9ED0, which is what we would expect for level 3-1!
最终得到了指针0x9ED0 它指向我们所预期的关卡3-1的精灵数据
We can do the same for the tile data.
图块数据指针的计算也是同样的原理
We use type index 1 again to get the 2nd entry in this table, which is 3.
再次根据关卡类型编码1 读取这个小数组的第2个元素 得到3
Add the level number 4 to 3 to get 7, and use index 7 to get the 8th level in the table,
将组内关卡编号4和3相加得到7 使用索引7读取图块数据指针数组的第8个元素
which is $A619, the pointer to level 3-1 again!
获得到的指针为0xA619 它正是关卡3-1的图块数据指针
The way you can tell something weird is going to happen when you try to load something like world 9
然而 试图加载9号世界的时候 事情开始变得不对劲起来
is by looking at the very first table of indices we made at the start.
问题从访问连续内存中的第一个数组 即关卡ID数组的索引数组时就产生了
We only accounted for 8 worlds, so this table is only 8 bytes long.
游戏只有8个世界 因此这个索引小数组的长度是8个字节
If we tried to find the 9th entry in this table, we'd overflow the table.
当试图寻找数组的第9个元素时 发生了向上越界
Before going all in with world 9, let's see what happens when we try to load world G.
暂且不谈9号世界的情况 先来看试图加载世界G时会发生什么
World G is equivalent to world 16.
世界G也就是十进制的第16个世界
If we try to find the 16th entry in this table, we go past the bounds of the table by 8 bytes.
当尝试读取数组的第16个元素时 越过了数组边界8个字节
Remember, these two tables are right next to each other in the ROM, so we just keep crusing to find the index we need.
值得注意的是 图中的两个数组在ROM中是紧邻的 跟随光标找到所需的索引
Index 15 of the first table overflows into the second table by 8 bytes,
第一个数组下标为15的元素越界进入了第二个数组 是第二个数组的第8个字节
so we get this $01 that normally corresponds to level 2-2.
读取到了0x01这个值 它原本是关卡2-2的关卡ID
However, in this context, it is instead being treated as an index in to the very table that it is part of.
然而 在当前上下文中 它被当成了自身所在的这个数组的索引
So now we use index 1 to find the 2nd entry in this table, which is this $29.
我们使用索引1 读取了这个数组的第2个元素 即0x29
This is the cutscene level that leads into level 1-2.
它对应连接关卡1-2的过场动画
And sure enough, if we try to play level G-1,
可以足够确定的是 如果尝试从关卡G-1开始游戏
we get the cutscene into level 1-2, though it is still called level G-1.
即使这一关会被称作关卡G-1 它会播放连接关卡1-2的过场动画
Now let's see what happens if we try to load in world 9.
现在 来看看在试图加载9号世界时会发生什么
So, the 9th entry into this table--we overflow by one byte, so our index is this $25.
这个数组的第9个元素溢出了1个字节 读取到的索引将会是0x25
We use this index $25 (or decimal 37) to find the 38th entry into this table of level IDs.
接下来使用索引25即十进制的37 来获取关卡ID数组的第38个元素
This table is only 36 bytes long! So we overflow this table as well--by two bytes.
由于这个数组只有36个字节 这次访问会溢出该数组2个字节的长度
The next thing in ROM is this small table for the offsets for the enemy data table.
ROM中后续的内容 是存储精灵数据指针数组的索引的那个小数组
The 2nd entry here is 6, so that is the level ID we are going to load.
其中第2个元素是6 接下来会把它当作需要装载关卡的ID
If we take a quick look at our big table again,
此时我们再次查询之前做的那个所有关卡ID的大表格
we can see that we will end up with the water version of level 6-2, but again, let's see why exactly that is.
可以看到这个关卡ID对应于一个关卡6-2的水下版本 下面来研究为什么会是这样吧
Now we expand this ID into binary.The type bits are 00, so this is a water level.
将关卡ID展开成二进制 关卡类型位是0b00 所以这是一个水下关卡
And the level number is 6.This means we are going to load in water level number 6,
组内关卡编号是6 意味着将装载水下关卡的第6关
which is interesting because there are only 3 water levels.
然而水下关卡只有3关 这就很有趣了
According to this table we made, the tile data for water level number 6 is the same tile data as the original 6-2!
根据此前做的这张表格 水下关卡第6关的图块数据和关卡6-2的一样
And the sprite data is loaded from some glitched pointer.
而精灵数据是某个“野指针”指向的内容
This is because if the take the level number 6 and add it to the offset for water levels in the sprite data pointer list,
这是由于将组内关卡编号6和水下关卡的精灵数据指针数组索引（0x1F）相加
we get an index of 37, which is greater than 33.
得到的索引是37 它大于33
The glitched pointer we get from this invalid index is actually $1C9D,
使用这个异常索引获得的指针是0x1C9D
which corresponds to system RAM rather than ROM.
指向的空间是系统内存而非游戏ROM
This is why glitched levels can be very volatile and possibly crash the game,
这解释了此类异常关卡十分脆弱且容易使游戏崩溃的现象
not only because it's possible to load in enemies with invalid IDs,
不仅容易载入具有无效标识符的敌人
but also because the level data can be changing while the game is playing!
而且关卡数据还会随着游玩发生变化
If you play around in level 9-1 a lot, you can start to notice that the game will crash somewhat frequently,
多玩几次关卡9-1就会发现 在这里游戏经常死机
and in a different spot every time.
并且每次死机的地点也不太一样
So if you can load errant enemy data,
既然能够载入有问题的精灵数据
can you load errant level tile data and get some fun glitch levels to explore?
那么载入有问题的关卡图块数据 得到的异常关卡又有哪些有趣的特性呢？
We'll save that for the final video of this 3-part mini-series on Super Mario Bros. glitched levels.
我们将它留到这个三集的《超级马里奥兄弟》“水下256关”迷你系列的最后一集来回答
In the next video, we'll look at those glitch levels you can get to, as well as the level format in general.
下期视频我们将继续探寻那些异常关卡 并系统介绍游戏关卡数据的格式
Thank you for watching!
感谢您的观看！
【译者：某科学的小姚同志；内容仅供技术交流，侵删，赞助和支持视频作者的方式在评论区中】
【正片结束，没有彩蛋 (≥﹏ ≤)】【如有错误请多多指点！翻译不易，求三连支持Orz】